<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-12-08T04:29:29-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Harriet Kim</title><entry><title type="html">Selfinity AI (Personal Database)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/selfinity-ai/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Selfinity AI (Personal Database)" /><published>2023-12-05T22:44:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-12-05T22:44:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/selfinity-ai</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/selfinity-ai/"><![CDATA[<div style="text-align: center;">
  <a href="https://github.com/harriet99/Selfinity_AI">GitHub</a>
</div>

<p><strong>This was a project for the AI ATL hackathon, and we won the second place.</strong></p>

<p>Check out our demo video:</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/9ljQDnSfQ00?start=0" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="">
</iframe>

<h2 id="-inspiration">💡 Inspiration</h2>

<p>Our project was inspired by a critical realization that resonated in both our personal and professional realms – the challenge of efficiently managing and accessing data.</p>

<p>In our personal lives, valuable hours that could be dedicated to loved ones are often lost in managing emails, social media, and numerous digital tasks. This universal challenge led us to envision a unified, AI-driven tool designed to streamline the management of digital information. Our goal was to create an assistant that simplifies these tasks and enhances personal life by efficiently organizing everyday digital interactions. Our vision was to develop a solution that could help reclaim these lost hours, transforming them into productive and meaningful time by managing personal data more efficiently.</p>

<p>In the professional world, we noticed a substantial drain on resources: employees frequently spend a significant amount of time navigating between various files and knowledge databases. This inefficiency is not only time-consuming but also costly. The onboarding process for new employees often translates into thousands to tens of thousands of dollars in training expenses and diverted attention from other staff. This investment continues until the employee becomes fully comfortable and competent in their role. The indirect costs, including the time senior employees spend explaining processes instead of focusing on their primary tasks, further amplify these expenses.</p>

<h2 id="-what-it-does">💎 What it does</h2>

<p>Our AI assistant serves as a comprehensive digital life co-pilot, redefining the way we interact with our digital lives. Its capabilities go beyond mere data consolidation; it actively assists in managing and interpreting information:</p>

<p>Diverse Service Integration: It connects with a range of services, including financial platforms through Plaid and email services via the Gmail API. This integration allows the assistant to pull relevant data from these services directly, providing a holistic view of your financial and communication landscapes.</p>

<p>Manual File Uploads: For data not automatically captured through service integrations, the assistant offers a manual upload feature. This allows you to directly upload files such as PDFs, documents, and other important data, ensuring that all your information can be centralized and accessed through the assistant.</p>

<p>Automated Browsing Data Collection: With your permission, the assistant can automatically scrape your browsing history and bookmarks. This feature is designed to gather data from your online activities, providing insights and summaries of the websites and resources you frequent. It’s an optional feature that you can enable or disable based on your privacy preferences.</p>

<p>User-Driven Customization: The level of integration and data collection is entirely under your control. You can choose which services to connect, what files to upload, and whether to enable automatic data scraping. This flexibility ensures that your assistant is tailored to your specific needs and comfort with data sharing.</p>

<p>Document Summarization and Connection Building: The assistant provides concise summaries and allows you to interact with you via chatbot interface. It intelligently links concepts and ideas across various articles and mediums of information, drawing connections that might otherwise go unnoticed, thereby enriching the user’s understanding and knowledge base. If you prefer to view them in a more standardized way, a customizable dashboard view will conveniently display your information.</p>

<p>Email Management: It sifts through your inbox, identifying and summarizing emails that require immediate attention. This feature not only saves time but ensures that important communications are not overlooked in the daily deluge of emails.</p>

<p>Calendar Management: The assistant keeps track of your schedule, bringing up calendar invites and reminders so that no important event or meeting is missed. This proactive approach to time management helps users stay organized and punctual.</p>

<p>Financial Insight: By analyzing your banking data, the AI assistant provides insights into your spending habits. It can identify trends, suggest budgets, and offer advice on financial decisions. This feature aims to promote better financial management and awareness, allowing users to make more informed choices about their spending.</p>

<p>In essence, our AI assistant is not just a tool for data organization; it’s an intelligent companion designed to optimize your digital interaction, saving time and reducing stress. By automating mundane tasks and providing insightful analysis, it allows users to focus on what truly matters, enhancing both professional efficiency and personal life quality.</p>

<h2 id="-how-we-built-it">🛠 How we built it</h2>

<p>Building our AI assistant was a complex process that combined state-of-the-art technologies and innovative methodologies:</p>

<p>Data Compilation Pipeline: We began with a Python pipeline to compile and collect diverse data sources, including browsing history, emails, and financial transactions. This step was crucial for creating a unified data format for further processing.</p>

<p>Pinecone Vector Database Integration: Post compilation, the data was processed and embedded into a Pinecone vector database, chosen for its efficiency in managing large volumes of vectorized data.</p>

<p>Embedding with OpenAI’s Ada Model: For embedding the data, we utilized OpenAI’s Ada model. Ada’s balance of performance and efficiency made it ideal for embedding our varied datasets while maintaining contextual relevance and accuracy.</p>

<p>Retrieval Augmented Generation Using GPT-4 Turbo: At the core of our AI assistant’s intelligence was the Retrieval Augmented Generation, powered by OpenAI’s GPT-4 Turbo model. This approach enabled dynamic interaction with the embedded data, ensuring accurate and contextually relevant responses.</p>

<p>Front End Development with Jinja2: We designed the user interface using Jinja2, a flexible and designer-friendly templating language for Python, enabling us to create a responsive and interactive front end.</p>

<p>Back End Development with FastAPI: FastAPI was our choice for the back end development. This modern, fast web framework was instrumental in building APIs with Python, ensuring efficient request handling and seamless integration with the front end.</p>

<p>LangChain for Language Model Integration: We incorporated LangChain, a framework specifically designed to facilitate the creation of applications using large language models. LangChain was instrumental in enhancing our assistant’s capabilities in document analysis, summarization, chatbot functionalities, and code analysis.</p>

<p>API Integrations: Our system integrated APIs like Gmail and Plaid for accessing email and financial data. We also created custom scripts for scraping browsing history and bookmarks, enriching the assistant’s data pool.</p>

<p>Security and Privacy Protocols: Given the sensitive nature of the data, we adhered to strict security and privacy protocols. All data handling and storage complied with top-tier data protection standards.</p>

<p>User-Centric Interface and Experience: The user interface, powered by Jinja2, was crafted with a focus on simplicity and intuitiveness. Features like a customizable dashboard and a chatbot interface made our assistant accessible and easy to use for a diverse user base.</p>

<h2 id="️-challenges-we-ran-into">️😰 Challenges we ran into</h2>

<p>Our journey in building the AI assistant was marked by a diverse array of challenges, each contributing to the project’s depth and sophistication:</p>

<p>Integrating Diverse Data Types: A major challenge was integrating various data types into a cohesive system. This task was particularly complex as we navigated the technical demands while supporting team members experiencing their first hackathon.</p>

<p>Optimization for GPT-4 Turbo Model: Tailoring the system to work efficiently with the GPT-4 Turbo model requires detailed and iterative optimization. Achieving high efficiency and accuracy in responses was a nuanced and ongoing process.</p>

<p>Connecting Multiple Services: We faced significant technical hurdles in integrating several services. This included the Gmail and Plaid APIs for accessing email and financial data, Pinecone for vector database management, LangChain for leveraging language models, and the OpenAI API for advanced AI functionalities. Each of these integrations was critical to ensure a comprehensive functionality and seamless user experience for our assistant.</p>

<p>Handling Large Arrays of Data and Token Usage: Managing a vast volume of data and optimizing token usage for data processing and API interactions posed a substantial challenge. Ensuring efficient data handling was crucial for system stability and responsiveness.</p>

<h2 id="️-accomplishments-that-were-proud-of">⭐️ Accomplishments that we’re proud of</h2>

<p>We take immense pride in our achievements with this project, especially considering the diversity of our team, which included many beginners and first-time hackathon participants. We successfully integrated a multitude of data types into a unified AI assistant that provides accurate and relevant responses. The ability of our system to handle a broad spectrum of queries with precision and efficiency stands as a testament to the robust integration of OpenAI’s technologies with our innovative data processing techniques. This accomplishment is particularly noteworthy given the varying levels of experience within our team, highlighting our collective growth and learning throughout this project.</p>

<h2 id="-whats-next">🔮 What’s next</h2>

<p>Our vision for the AI assistant extends beyond its current capabilities, as we aim to develop it into a commercially viable product that appeals to both B2B and B2C markets. This ambitious goal involves a series of strategic steps:</p>

<p>Iterative Development and User Feedback: We plan to engage in numerous iterations and extensive user interviews. This process is vital for refining our understanding of the value proposition and ensuring that our product aligns with the needs and expectations of our users.</p>

<p>Expanding Functionalities: To enhance user experience and utility, we will introduce new features such as:
YouTube Video Scraping, Integration with Fitness and Health Apps, Auto-generated To-Do Lists, Automatic Responses and Task Completions, Media Suggestions, and Messenger Compilations.</p>

<p>Product-Market Fit: A key focus will be on finding the product-market fit that effectively addresses the pain points of our customers, improving outcomes in their personal and professional lives.</p>

<p>User-Centric Approach: By continuously iterating based on user feedback and adapting our strategies, we aim to make our assistant a solution that not only manages digital information but also provides meaningful and practical assistance.</p>

<p>Our journey ahead involves adapting and innovating to create a product that is technologically sophisticated, intuitive, and impactful. The goal is to make our AI assistant a fundamental part of users’ lives, enriching their experiences through advanced information management and insightful assistance, tailored to their unique needs and preferences.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="fastapi" /><category term="gcp" /><category term="google-gmail-oauth" /><category term="huggingface" /><category term="jinja" /><category term="langchain" /><category term="openai" /><category term="pinecone" /><category term="plaid" /><category term="python" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[GitHub]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/markdown.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/markdown.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Hive Guardian</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/hive-guardian/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hive Guardian" /><published>2022-05-10T22:44:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-05-10T22:44:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/hive-guardian</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/hive-guardian/"><![CDATA[<div style="text-align: center;">
  <a href="https://github.com/harriet99/Tower-Jackets">GitHub</a>
</div>

<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2>

<p>I decided to create a <strong>Power Defense Game</strong>—a tower defense style mobile game developed in <strong>Java</strong> using <strong>Android Studio</strong>. This project served as a comprehensive exploration of game design principles, programming techniques, and user experience testing.</p>

<h2 id="why-a-tower-defense-game">Why a Tower Defense Game?</h2>

<p>I think tower defense games offer a unique blend of strategy, resource management, and spatial reasoning. By choosing this project, I aimed to:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Learn how to structure a larger-scale Android application beyond simple layouts.</li>
  <li>Explore game development frameworks and the Android lifecycle for rendering and updates.</li>
  <li>Enhance my understanding of object-oriented programming principles by implementing various game entities.</li>
  <li>Develop a fun, interactive project that I could share with others and iterate on.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="core-skill-sets-utilized">Core Skill Sets Utilized</h2>

<p>Throughout the development process, I relied heavily on:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Java Programming</strong>:<br />
Implementing game logic, object-oriented design patterns, and managing data structures for enemies, towers, and game states.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Android Studio &amp; Android Framework</strong>:<br />
Designing interactive UI screens, handling user input, managing the activity lifecycle, and rendering game elements.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Game Loop and Rendering</strong>:<br />
Creating a consistent and efficient update-render loop, ensuring smooth game performance on mobile devices.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Resource Management</strong>:<br />
Handling assets such as images, sound effects, and screen configurations for different devices.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Testing and Debugging</strong>:<br />
Using Android emulators and real devices for testing gameplay, debugging performance issues, and refining the user experience.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<h2 id="how-the-game-works">How the Game Works</h2>

<p>At a high level, this tower defense game tasks the player with defending a hive (the “monument”) from incoming enemies that travel along a predefined path. Players start with a certain amount of currency (coins) and must strategically place towers to prevent enemies from reaching the hive. If too many enemies reach the end and the hive’s health drops to zero, the player loses.</p>

<h3 id="game-flow">Game Flow</h3>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Welcome &amp; Configuration Screen</strong>:<br />
On startup, the player is greeted with a welcome screen that allows them to:
    <ul>
      <li>Start the game.</li>
      <li>Quit the application.</li>
    </ul>

    <p>After starting, the player must enter their name (no empty names allowed) and choose a difficulty level. Difficulty affects:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>Starting money.</li>
      <li>Hive (monument) health.</li>
      <li>Tower costs.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Game Screen Setup</strong>:
Once configured, the player is shown the initial map:
    <ul>
      <li>Displays the path enemies will follow.</li>
      <li>Shows the hive’s health and starting money.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Buying &amp; Placing Towers</strong>:
Players can buy three types of towers, each with a unique benefit:
    <ul>
      <li><strong>Bee Tower</strong>: Attacks enemies within range, decreasing their health.</li>
      <li><strong>Heart Tower</strong>: Boosts the hive’s health, increasing survivability.</li>
      <li><strong>Coin Tower</strong>: Generates additional coins over time, increasing the player’s available resources.</li>
    </ul>

    <p>The player must ensure towers are placed off the path. Towers cannot be placed without sufficient funds, and tower costs vary by difficulty.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Starting Combat</strong>:
After placement, the player can start combat. Enemies appear at the start of the path and move towards the hive. When an enemy reaches the hive, the hive’s health decreases.</p>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Combat &amp; Enemy Interactions</strong>:
    <ul>
      <li><strong>Attacking</strong>: Bee Towers automatically attack enemies within range. As enemies lose health, they eventually disappear when their health reaches zero.</li>
      <li><strong>Resource Gain</strong>: Coin Towers periodically grant more coins, allowing further expansion of defenses.</li>
      <li><strong>Upgrades</strong>: Towers can be upgraded to improve their stats (e.g., Bee Tower can get increased range or damage).</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Victory &amp; Defeat</strong>:
    <ul>
      <li>Over time, a <strong>final boss</strong> enemy appears, tougher than all previous ones. Defeating this boss leads to a victory screen, showing game statistics and allowing a restart.</li>
      <li>If the hive’s health reaches zero, the player is shown a game over screen with statistics and the option to restart.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ol>

<h2 id="demonstration">Demonstration</h2>

<h3 id="video-demo">Video Demo</h3>

<p>Check out the gameplay demo here:</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/qmmNwiEN9Uo" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="">
</iframe>

<h2 id="challenges--lessons-learned">Challenges &amp; Lessons Learned</h2>

<p><strong>Challenges</strong>:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Balancing enemy health, tower damage, and coin generation to ensure the game is fun and not too easy or too hard.</li>
  <li>Handling device compatibility and performance optimizations, ensuring smooth rendering and animations.</li>
  <li>Creating a user-friendly interface that clearly communicates game state, health, money, and other resources.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Lessons Learned</strong>:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Modularity &amp; OOP Practices</strong>: Maintaining clean code with modular classes for enemies, towers, and UI screens made it easier to extend the game.</li>
  <li><strong>User Experience Importance</strong>: Simple interfaces and clear visual feedback significantly improve player engagement.</li>
  <li><strong>Iterative Design</strong>: Repeated testing and feedback helped refine difficulty settings, improve tower placement UX, and enhance the upgrade system.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>This tower defense project was a rewarding experience that combined programming, design, and user experience considerations. I learned a great deal about structuring a game loop, managing resources, and providing meaningful visual feedback to the player. The final result is a playable and (I hope) enjoyable tower defense game that I can continue to refine and build upon in the future.</p>

<p>If you’re interested, give the demo a watch, or try it out if it becomes available. Thanks for reading!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[GitHub]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/markdown.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/markdown.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>